人終難免一死？
Must we die?
宇宙中有沒有長生不死的生物
Are there beings in the cosmos who live forever...
可以永遠逍遙地游在時間之河上？
afloat on an endless journey down the river of time?
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第十一集
我們的先祖依靠的是月亮與星星為時間分段時
Our ancestors marked the passage of time by the Moon and stars.
可在大約5000年前 在這裏生活過的人們
But it was the people who once lived here, around 5,000 years ago,
他們開始把時間分為
who first starting chopping up time
小時和分鐘這樣更小的部分
into smaller bite-sized portions of hours and minutes.
當時這個地方叫做烏魯克
They call this place Uruk.
我們現在稱之為伊拉克
We call it Iraq.
這裏是位於底格里斯河與幼發拉底河之間
It's a part of Mesopotamia,
美索不達米亞平原的一部分
the land between the Tigris and the Euphrates rivers.
人們在這裏創建了城市
The city was invented here.
在與時間無盡的戰鬥中
And one of humanity's greatest victories was won
取得了人類歷史上一個偉大的成就
in the ceaseless battle against time.
人類在這裏學會了如何書寫
It was here that we learned how to write.
死亡再也不能讓人默默無聞
Death could no longer silence us.
書寫給予了人類力量
And writing gave us the power
讓我們可以逾越千年
to reach across the millennia
與古人交流精神
and speak inside the heads of the living.
歷史上沒有人
No one has ever spoken
能穿越如此之長的時間之河
across a longer stretch of time's river
除了阿卡德帝國的公主
than this Akkadian princess,
她是歷史上第一位君王的女兒
daughter of the first emperor in history,
也被稱為月亮公主——恩西杜安娜
and priestess of the Moon-- Enheduanna.
她不僅僅會寫詩歌
For not only did she write poetry,
恩西杜安娜還做了其他一些
but Enheduanna did something
前人沒有做過的事情
no one before her had ever done--
她在作品上署上自己的名字
she signed her name to her work.
可以說 她是歷史上第一個
She's the first person for whom we can say
我們知道確切身份
we know who she was,
也知道她的夢想世界的人
and what she dreamed.
她一直夢想著能走進神奇之門
She dreamt of stepping through the Gate of Wonder.
這就是恩西杜安娜所想
Here's a thought Enheduanna sent
它穿越了4000年的時光來到我們身邊
across more than 4,000 years to you.
下面就是她的作品
It's from her work entitled
名為《小女雄心》
Lady of the Largest Heart.
英娜娜 天上的金星
Innana, the planet Venus,
愛的女神
goddess of love, will have a great destiny
你是宇宙偉大的主宰
throughout the entire universe.
宇宙的主宰
...throughout the entire universe.
烏魯克也是史詩
And Uruk is also the place where the epic tale
《英雄的旅程》首次創作的地方
of "The Hero's Journey" was first written down.
遠在蝙蝠俠 天行者盧克
Before Batman, Luke Skywalker,
奧德賽——這些英雄誕生之前
Odysseus-- before them all--
傳說有一個人叫吉爾伽美什
there was a man named Gilgamesh
他為了能征服時間而遠離了家鄉
who left home on a quest to vanquish time.
吉爾伽美什尋覓著長生不死的方法
Gilgamesh was searching for immortality.
他走遍四方
He looked everywhere,
獲得了無上的智慧
gained complete wisdom,
發現了隱藏的秘密
uncovered what was hidden.
他帶著一堆大洪水時代之前的傳奇回到了家鄉
He brought back a tale of times before the Great Flood.
他建造了後世的君王沒有能與他媲美的烏魯克城池
He built the Wall of Uruk, which no future king will ever match.
吉爾伽美什的故事
Read the story of that man Gilgamesh,
描述了一個在烏魯克誕生的英雄
a hero born of Uruk,
他經歷了千辛萬苦
who went through all kinds of sufferings.
遠渡重洋
Who crossed the ocean,
去到太陽升起的地方
the broad seas, as far as the sunrise;
世界的盡頭
who inspected the edges of the world,
只為了尋覓永生的奧秘
searching for eternal life.
在旅途中
On his travels,
吉爾伽美什遇到了一位名為烏特納比西丁的智者
Gilgamesh encountered a wise man named Utnapishtim,
智者告訴了他大洪水曾把世界毀滅
who told him the story of a flood that destroyed the world,
一位神明指示烏特納比西丁
and how one of the gods instructed Utnapishtim
造出方舟 拯救他的家人與動物
to build an ark to rescue his family and the animals.
這就是世界上最早的關於大洪水的傳說
The earliest surviving account of the flood legend
它產生於美索不達米亞
was written down in Mesopotamia,
直到1000年後
a thousand years before it was retold
《聖經·舊約》中才出現諾亞方舟的故事
as the story of Noah in the Old Testament.
可以這麼說
So, you could say Gilgamesh
吉爾伽美什圓滿地完成了他對永生的追求
fulfilled his quest for immortality.
這就是今天的《吉爾伽美什史詩》
We still read the Epic of Gilgamesh,
人們每讀一次 他就再生一次
and with every reader, he lives again.
自從人類第一部英雄史詩誕生以來
And all those heroes and superheroes who have come since
歷史上還涌現出無數的英雄與超級英雄
follow in the footsteps of the first hero's journey--
這可被視為某種形式的永生
another kind of immortality;
隨人類文明而流傳的故事
a story sent from one civilization to another
跨越千年
across thousands of years.
但生命本身也有自己的故事
But life itself sends its own stories
流傳了好幾百萬年
across billions of years.
它就是我們每個人體內都攜帶的信息
It's a message that every one of us carries inside,
烙印在我們的細胞之中
inscribed in all the cells of our bodies,
它用地球上的生命都知曉的語言書寫
in a language that all life on Earth can read.
基因的密碼表上
The genetic code is written in an alphabet
只有4個字母
consisting of only four letters.
每個字母代表著由原子組成的一個分子
Each letter is a molecule made of atoms;
每個單詞由3個字母組成
each word is three letters long.
每個生命都是了不起的傑作
Every living thing is a masterpiece,
由自然書寫 進化所編輯
written by nature and edited by evolution;
它的運行與複製
the instructions for running and reproducing
經由精密的生命機器所操縱
the intricate machinery of life.
生命的基本信息
The essential message of life
已經被反覆複製了3百萬年
has been copied and recopied for more than 3 billion years.
但這些信息從何而來？
But where did that message come from?
無人知曉
Nobody knows.
也許它就誕生於這樣一個陽光照射的淺水塘
Perhaps it began in a shallow, sunlit pool, just like this.
不知何時起
Somehow, carbon-rich molecules
富碳分子開始使用能量來對自身進行粗陋的複製
began using energy to make crude copies of themselves.
某些分子變體具有更好的複製能力
Some varieties were better at making copies,
並留下了更多的後代
and left more offspring.
分子間的競爭讓它們變得日益精巧
The competing molecules became more elaborate.
進化與生命由此悄然而生
Evolution and life itself was underway.
或許 生命是源於
Or life could've started
灼熱的火山口邊上
in the searing heat of a volcanic vent
深藏於海底
on the deep sea floor.
甚至有沒有可能 生命是搭著順風車自天而降
Or is it possible that life came to Earth
來到地球的呢
as a hitchhiker?
讓我來跟你說個故事
Let me tell you a story
關於另一個世界的旅行者的故事
about a traveler from another world.
在亞歷山大附近有一個寧靜的埃及小村莊
The peace of the Egyptian village of Nakhla,
叫納卡垃
near Alexandria,
在1911年6月的某個清晨 突然天降隕災
was abruptly shattered on a June morning in 1911.
在這塊隕石上記載著
Written in this meteorite was
來自另一個星球的信息
a message from another planet.
但直到70年後
But 70 years would pass
人們才懂得如何解讀
before anyone could read it.
1976年
In 1976,
美國航天局將兩艘維京號探測器送上了火星
NASA landed two Viking spacecraft on Mars.
卡爾·薩根把我們引向那裏
Carl Sagan took us there
在人類探索宇宙的早期
on our original journey through the cosmos.
我們發現火星的大氣
We found that the Martian air
比地球稀薄
was less than one percent as dense as ours,
大部分由二氧化碳組成
and made mostly of carbon dioxide.
還有小部分的氮
There were smaller amounts of nitrogen,
氬 水蒸氣與氧氣
argon, water vapor and oxygen.
幾年後
A few years later,
當科學家們想要分析
when scientists thought to analyze the gasses
納卡拉隕石中含有的氣體
trapped inside the Nakhla meteorite,
與及其它的物質成分時
and other members of its class,
他們發現了驚人的相似性
they found a striking similarity--
大部分的隕石
the vast majority of meteorites
是小行星的碎片
are fragments of asteroids.
但落在地球上的這塊納卡拉隕石
But the kind that hit Nakhla, on Earth,
只有可能來自一個地方……
could only have come from one place...
那就是火星
Mars.
歡迎來到火星
Welcome to Mars.
十億年前 這裏的一座火山爆發了
Over a billion years ago, a volcano erupted here
岩漿冷卻後形成了岩石
and its lava cooled into solid rock.
幾百萬年後
Hundreds of millions of years later,
這塊地方被洪水所淹沒
this area was flooded with water.
洪水過後很多年
And long after that flood,
一塊有直布羅佗岩石那麼大的小行星
an asteroid the size of the Rock of Gibraltar
撞擊了火星表面
crashed into the Martian surface,
炸出一個大坑
blasting out a huge crater.
大部分的碎片被彈到太空
Much of the debris was ejected back out into space,
碎片一開始繞著太陽旋轉
where it orbited the Sun until a gravitational tug
直到來自火星的引力把其中一個石塊
from its home planet, Mars, diverted one of the boulders
轉向與地球碰撞的軌道
into a collision course with Earth.
它最終抵達了納卡拉村
Its arrival shook up the little village of Nakhla.
像納卡拉這樣類型的隕石
Meteorites of the type that hit Nakhla
就是星際間天然的運輸系統
are the vehicles of a natural interplanetary transit system
它在行星之間輸送石塊
that sends rocks between the planets.
像這樣的隕石可以把微小的"貨物"安全運抵目的地
Such a meteorite can safely shelter microscopic cargo--
那就是生命的種子
the seeds of life--
它就是星際方舟
an interplanetary ark.
大部分的岩石是多孔的 有細小的角落和縫隙
Most rocks are porous, full of tiny nooks and crannies,
很適合生命用來偷渡
where life can stow away.
我們已經發現好幾種微生物
We know that some microbes can survive
能在惡劣的太空環境下生存
the hostile environment of space.
比如說 像這些小夥伴們
Take these guys, for instance.
這些微生物
These microbes spent a year and a half riding
在國際空間站外放置了一年半
on the outside of the International Space Station,
它們暴露在極端的溫度與真空下
exposed to the extreme temperatures, vacuum,
還有宇宙幅射
and radiation of space.
但它們中的一部分在被帶回到地球之後
And some of them were still alive and kicking
仍然生龍活虎
when they were brought back to Earth.
這些生物還有更令人驚異的一面
Even more astonishing are these creatures,
它們能從800萬年的假死狀態中甦醒
awakened from a deathlike sleep of eight million years.
它們曾被冰封在南極
They were frozen in the Antarctic ice
在人類出現前好幾百萬年就已存在
millions of years before our species even existed.
而且它們依然活著
And they're still alive.
如果生命能經受住惡劣的太空環境
If life can withstand the hardships of space
並且千年不死的話
and endure for millennia,
那它們就能乘坐著星際快車
then it could ride the natural interplanetary transit system
從一個世界到另一個世界
from world to world.
很有可能 我們的微生物先祖們
It's a good bet that our microbial ancestors
就是這樣從太空降臨
spent some time in space.
為什麼我們會如此認為？
Why do we think so?
地球有45億年的歷史
The Earth is four-and-a-half- billion-years old.
在它的誕生初期有一半的時間
For the first half of its lifetime,
都在被巨型小行星轟炸著
large asteroids were bombarding the planet
劫難每隔幾百萬年就來一次
every few million years.
最猛烈的衝擊可以讓海洋蒸發
The most violent impacts vaporized the oceans
讓地表的岩石融化
and even melted the surface rock.
每一次如此巨大的衝擊
Each such collision would have
都能讓星球上的生命全滅
completely sterilized the planet
並持續好幾千年
for thousands of years.
但我們從化石中得知
But we know from fossils in the rocks
細菌早已在地球上生存
that bacteria were evolving on Earth
從那段地球形成的早期就已開始
during this formative period.
那生命又是如何逃過這些劫難的呢？
So how could life have survived such a lethal series of blows?
任何一次巨大的小行星衝擊地球時
Whenever one of those big asteroids
爆炸都會形成大坑
hit the Earth, the explosion would blast out a crater,
將幾百萬塊巨石彈入太空
launching millions of boulders into space.
許多石頭當中有細菌存在
Many of those rocks carried living bacteria inside.
有些小生物就能像這樣生存在太空中
Some of the bugs would have survived in space,
而它們留在地球上的同類早已被烤焦了
while all those left behind on Earth would have been fried.
撞擊過後幾千年
A few thousand years after each impact,
地球又冷卻下來
the Earth would have cooled down enough
水凝聚為海洋
for water to condense into oceans.
地球又變得適宜居住了
The planet would again be habitable.
與此同時 在太空中的大部分石頭
Meanwhile, most of the rocks launched into space
正在繞著太陽轉
would have been orbiting the Sun.
它們當中的一部分將會重新與地球相遇
Some of them would encounter the Earth again,
像隕石一樣進入地球大氣
reenter the atmosphere as meteorites,
將它們攜帶的珍貴生命
and deliver their precious cargo of life
重新播灑到這個行星上
to re-seed the planet...
如同諾亞方舟
like Noah's ark.
如果生命不能
What this means is that life doesn't have
像這樣從絕世天劫中重新開始的話
to start over again from scratch after each catastrophe.
它還能從其他地方再來一次
It can pick up where it left off.
當時太陽系還很年輕
When the solar system was young,
金星可能更像地球
Venus was probably more like Earth,
有海洋 甚至有生命
with oceans and maybe even life.
金星 地球 火星都由於隕石衝擊
Venus, Earth, and Mars were all exchanging rocks
而在互相傳送石頭
with each other, due to asteroid impacts.
地球上的生命有沒有
Does life on Earth carry any traces
攜帶著這些遙遠的星際迷航的線索？
of interplanetary voyages made in the distant past?
為什麼有些微生物能
Why is it that some microbes can survive
在強烈的輻射與真空的太空中活著？
the intense radiation and vacuum of space?
這樣的環境根本就不在地球上存在過
These conditions don't naturally exist on Earth.
也許這些小生物在告訴我們
Maybe those bugs are telling us
它們的先祖從幾百萬年前開始
that their ancestors survived those same conditions in space,
就已經是這樣在太空中活著
a few billion years ago.
既然我們知道了微生物能通過石頭
So we know that microbes can stow away in rocks
在行星之間飛渡
and survive the voyage from planet to planet.
那有沒有可能從恆星到恆星？
But what about trip from star to star--
實現更廣闊的星系旅行？
an interstellar odyssey?
蒲公英
The dandelion.
有3000萬年的歷史
Around 30 million years ago,
它擁有把自身的生命信息傳遞出去的不同方式
it evolved another way to send its own message of life
那就是通過時空
through space and time.
每一個種子都是一個小傘兵
Each seedling is a little paratrooper,
它漂浮在空氣中
floating on the wind,
上下浮沉 尋找一個安全之所
risking everything for a safe place to land.
上升氣流能把它們帶到高空
Updrafts can carry them higher into the air.
蒲公英能穿越數十
A dandelion can travel dozens,
或者是數百公里
possibly hundreds of kilometers,
甚至能跨過高山
even crossing over mountain ranges.
進化將它塑造成為精妙的飛行器
Evolution has shaped it into an exquisite flying machine.
它的種子就是另一種方舟
The seed is another kind or ark,
確保物種得以存活
ensuring the survival of its species
乘風飄往安全之地
by riding the currents of the atmosphere to safe harbors.
每個種子裏的DNA都藏著一個故事
Each seed in its DNA carries a story,
那就是下一代蒲公英的特徵與命運
the character and destiny of the next dandelion--
生命通過複製自身而傳播出去
life propagates by retelling its story.
那生命有沒有可能
Is it possible that life could survive the journey
在恆星到恆星的旅行中存活下來？
from star to star?
恆星之間的距離要比
The stars are about a million times farther apart
行星之間的距離多出一百萬倍
from each other than are the planets.
距離是如此的遙遠 以至於要好幾百萬年後
Space is so vast that it would take billions of years
地球的石頭才會抵達那裏
for a rock ejected from the Earth
然後與圍繞另一顆恆星運轉的行星相遇
to collide with a planet circling another star.
沒有微生物能夠
Any stowaway microbes would never survive
在如此長時間的宇宙幅射下存活
the cosmic radiation for that long.
但有一個可行的方案
But there's a plausible scenario
可以實現生命從太陽系向另一星系的傳播
for how life could spread from one solar system to another.
銀河系的恆星受引力的驅動
The stars of the Milky Way are drawn by gravity
它們在自己的巨大軌道中繞著銀河中心運行
in their own enormous orbits around its center.
比如我們的太陽
Our Sun, for example,
每隔2億2千5百萬年就完成一次軌道運行
takes some 225 million years to complete a single orbit.
在每次繞銀河系公轉中
During each revolution around the galaxy,
太陽系會穿越2到3個
our solar system will pass through two or three
巨大的星際雲
gigantic interstellar clouds,
每個星際雲都有好幾光年寬
each of them many light years across.
銀河系是一個巨大的星球工廠
Galaxies are world-making machines.
我們的銀河中有超過100個這樣的大型星雲
Our Milky Way has more than 100 of these vast clouds,
氣體和塵埃在那裏聚集
a place where gas and dust condense
形成新的恆星與行星
to form new stars and planets.
在銀河的旅途中
In its travels through the Milky Way,
太陽不僅由其行星相伴
our Sun is accompanied not only by its planets,
而且還有數以萬億的遙遠的彗星跟隨
but also by a trillion distant comets.
當太陽系穿過星際雲時
When our solar system passes through an interstellar cloud,
巨大星雲的引力
the gravity of the massive cloud
牽動了最外層的彗星
stirs up the outermost comets.
有些彗星被扔出到
Some comets will be hurled out
恆星間的空間
into the space between the stars.
有些則被拉進了
Others will plunge inward...
直奔太陽的路線
falling towards the Sun.
它們中的一部分可能會與行星相撞
And some of them may collide with the planets.
彗星以高速碰撞了多岩石的行星
The high-speed impact of a comet with a rocky planet
將大量的石頭拋入太空
will launch boulders like rockets into space.
如果這個星球上正好有生命存在
If that planet should happen to be inhabited,
那麼這許多的石頭中就會有乘客
many of those rocks will carry passengers--
活的微生物
living microbes.
幾千年後
After thousands of years,
地球石頭的碎塊
fragments of the rocks ejected from Earth
會像隕石一樣落在新生的行星上
can fall as meteors into the atmospheres of newborn planets
就在那星際雲裏
in the interstellar cloud.
那些偷渡的微生物們
If the stowaway microbes
如果正好遇到了液態水
should happen to come in contact with liquid water,
它們就會開始復甦並不斷複製
they can revive and reproduce.
生命也許就是這樣
This may be how life comes barreling
進入另一個荒蕪的天地
into the barren places.
太陽也是由星雲聚集而成
The sun emerges from the cloud,
它把生命的種子
having scattered the seeds of life
散播在其它恆星的新生世界中
among the newborn worlds of other stars.
這些新世界現在被生命所觸及
Those new worlds, now touched by life,
然後離開它們誕生的星雲
will then leave their birth cloud
從此天各一方
and go their separate ways.
最終 這些恆星又會把它們
Eventually, their stars will carry them
帶到其它的星際雲那裏
through other interstellar clouds,
也許它們又將散播生命到更多的新世界中
where they may seed still more new worlds.
想像一下 如果這樣的過程在不同的星球之間重複
Imagine this process repeated from world to world,
每一次都把生命帶給另一個世界
each one bringing life to others.
生命就以這樣緩慢的鏈式反應傳播開來
Life would then propagate, like a slow chain reaction,
佈滿整個銀河
through the entire galaxy.
生命也許就是如此降臨地球
This could be how life came to Earth.
可我們還不能確定
We do not know for sure.
外面是否有像我們一樣的生物？
Are there any beings out there like us?
他們是否也在問同樣的問題？
Do they ask the same questions?
他們也會害怕嗎？
Do they share our fears?
他們是否也有英雄與傳奇？
Do they have heroes and adventures?
如果他們存在 又在哪裏？
If they do exist, where are they?
他們又如何顯示他們的存在？
How might they make their presence known?
人類是如何第一次宣佈自己在銀河系的存在？
How did we first announce our presence to the galaxy?
1946年 二戰結束後的第二年
It was 1946, the year after the Second World War ended.
再生動的想像力
The vivid imaginations
就算是威爾斯的小說和巴克•羅傑斯的探險
of HG Wells and Buck Rogers
它們的瘋狂也比不上
never cooked up a more fantastic experience
我們軍隊的工程師
than the Army engineers
在新澤西州貝爾馬實驗室裏幹的事
at their laboratory in Belmar, New Jersey.
它為人類開啟了
It opens up unlimited possibilities
星際探險的無限可能性
for interstellar experiment.
美國的工程師們
American engineers
向月球發送了一束無線電波
bounced a beam of radio waves off the Moon,
並成功地檢測到了它的回波
and were able to detect its echo.
他們把這項實驗稱為戴安娜計劃
They called this experiment Project Diana.
這是由人類發出的首次
It was the first interstellar message
星際信息傳遞
ever sent by our species...
那是一段聽起來很怪異的鐘聲
an eerie, tolling bell.
只要發揮一下無限的想像力
If one allows the imagination free reign,
無限的可能性會涌現出來
many future possibilities appear.
載人太空飛船上
Spaceships, carrying passengers
當它以每小時數千英里的速度行駛時
it thousands of miles per hour,
我們能有效地控制它
can be controlled
並且建立起通訊連接
and communication established
與飛船上的乘客交談
with their passengers,
因為現在我們已經知道了
for we now know that the Earth's atmosphere
地球的大氣是可以被穿透的
can be penetrated.
物體以光速行進時
Traveling at the speed of light,
只需要1秒鐘
it takes just over one second
就能讓無線電波抵達月面
for a radio wave to reach the lunar surface.
但擴散開來的波陣面比月球更大
But the expanding wavefront is much bigger than the Moon.
大部分的電波會從月球旁邊經過
Most of the wave passes right by it,
只有中央部位的電波會反彈回來
but the central part gets bounced back.
經過2.5秒的來回時間後
After a round-trip travel time of two and a half seconds,
電波回到了地球
it hits our planet.
戴安娜計劃傳輸了
Project Diana transmitted
一連串的強烈無線電波
a series of powerful radio waves--
每隔4秒發送1次
one every four seconds--
好比是我們在"Ping"月亮
to "ping" the Moon.
ping:用來測試數據包能否通過IP協議到達特定主機
那些沒有抵達月亮的電波仍會繼續旅行
The parts that missed the Moon are traveling still.
這僅僅是個開端
It was just the beginning.
二戰後
After World War II,
美國各地的電視台遍地開花
television stations cropped up all over the United States,
世界各地也同樣如此
and other parts of the world.
戴安娜計劃發送的信息
The Project Diana message
FM廣播、電視與雷達發送的信號
and the FM radio, television and radar signals
在20世紀中
of the 20th century
早已以光速向外四處發送
all move outward at the speed of light.
這些信號組成了巨大的一個無線電波層
These transmissions make up a vast sphere of radio waves,
在地球之外向四周擴張
expanding away from the Earth in all directions.
可以說 我們的世界
You could say that our world
正在向外廣播故事
is radiating stories.
我們的祖先把吉爾伽美什的故事
Our ancestors etched the story of Gilgamesh
刻在泥板上
into clay tablets,
以此把傳奇流傳到未來
sending that epic tale into the future.
我們則是把故事轉為無線電波
We've encoded our stories in radio waves
發送到太空中去
and beamed them into space.
它們每年要走1光年
They cover one light-year of distance--
也就是6萬億英里
that's six trillion miles--
自從它們被發送出去的那一刻起
for every year of time since they were sent.
人類已經像這樣向太空發送信息
We've been sending our stories into space
超過70年了
for over 70 years.
最先發出的電波
The leading edge of these signals
已經橫掃了
has already washed over
其它恆星的幾千個行星
thousands of planets of other stars.
如果這些星球上的文明
If any of these worlds are home
擁有無線電望遠鏡的話
to a civilization with radio telescopes,
他們可能已經知道我們在這裏
they could already know that we're here.
如果其他的世界也能夠發送
What if other worlds are sending
他們的故事到太空中 又會怎樣？
their stories into space?
自從1960年以來 人類一直在監聽
Since 1960, we've been listening
來自外太空的無線電信號
for extraterrestrial radio signals
不過還沒有聽到什麼像鐘聲那樣的東西
without hearing so much as a tolling bell.
不過我們的研究還過於零散
But our search has been sporadic
只局限於天空中的某個部分
and limited to certain parts of the sky.
現在我們知道
For all we know,
我們也許錯過了某些外星人的信號
we may have just missed an alien signal,
因為我們找的是錯誤的地點
looking in the wrong place
在錯誤的時間
at the wrong time.
我們監聽的只是很小的一個部分
We've only listened to a miniscule fraction
對於我們銀河系的星球來說
of the stars in our galaxy.
或許還有其他的問題
And there may be another problem...
我們人類從某些方面來說
we are, to some extent,
是時代的囚徒
prisoners of our own moment in time
受困於我們的科技水平
and the limits of our technology.
無線電與電視廣播
Radio and television broadcasting
也許只是在人類的科技發展史中
may be only a brief passing phase
一個很簡單的階段
in our technological development.
當我們設想著外星文明
When we imagine alien civilizations
也在用無線電望遠鏡發送著信號的時候
broadcasting signals with radio telescopes,
我們又和那些
are we any different from earlier generations
設想著乘坐炮彈飛到月球的先人有什麼不同?
who imagined riding cannon shells to the Moon?
比人類更先進的外星文明
Civilizations even slightly more advanced than ours
也許已經發展到
may have already moved on
另外一種通訊模式了
to some other mode of communication,
一種我們還不知道
one that we have yet to discover
更無法想像的方式
or even imagine.
他們的信息很有可能
Their messages could be
此刻就圍繞在我們的周圍
swirling around us, at this very moment,
可我們不懂得怎麼去捕獲它
but we lack the means to perceive them,
就像我們的祖先一樣
just as all of our ancestors,
在一個多世紀以前
up to a little more than a century ago,
人們經常會察覺不到
would have been oblivious to the most urgent radio signal
從別的地方傳來的無線電呼救信號
from another world.
還有一個更棘手的可能性
But there's another, more troubling possibility--
文明和生命體一樣
civilizations, like other living things,
由於自然的原因或者是暴力
may only live so long before perishing
或者是自行造成的毀滅
due to natural causes, or violence,
在生存過一段時間以後便會消亡
or self-inflicted wounds.
不管怎樣 我們已經盡力
Whether or not we ever make contact
嘗試去接觸外星文明
with intelligent alien life
這可能取決於另一個重要的問題
may depend on a critical question.
一個文明的壽命有多長？
What is the life expectancy of a civilization?
恩西杜拉娜的年代
By the time of Enheduanna,
也就是人類歷史上最早出現借貸的年代
the first person to ever get a writing credit,
當時文明已經存在超過了一千年
civilization was already more than 1,000 years old.
但今天 她那輝煌的城市只是一堆荒蕪的廢墟
But today, her glorious city is a barren wasteland.
是哪裏出了差錯？
What went wrong?
其中一個重要的原因就是發生在美索不達亞平原的城邦之間的那些
One problem was the almost ceaseless warfare
無休止的戰爭
between the cities of Mesopotamia,
摧毀了人類的成就
which continually destroyed their achievements.
偉大的軍功
They glorified military conquest
使它最終成為了犧牲品
and ultimately became its victims.
另一個消亡的原因
Another cause of decline
是他們的技術知識
was that their technical know-how
遠遠超過了他們對自然的理解
overran their understanding of nature.
巧妙的灌溉系統
The ingenious irrigation system that was the basis
是美索不達米亞偉大文明的基礎
for the great civilizations of Mesopotamia
但也引發了一個意想不到的結果
had an unintended consequence--
每年水都會經過管道進入他們的農田
the water channeled into their farmlands every year
水蒸發後會有鹽留下來
evaporated and left its salt behind.
經過幾代人的時間後 積累下來的鹽
Over generations, the salt accumulated
會讓莊稼枯死
and began to kill the crops.
然後 在大約公元前2200年
And then, about 2,200 BC,
就在恩西杜拉娜的時代過後不久
not long after the time of Enheduanna,
災難降臨
disaster struck...
劫難一樣的乾旱來臨
a drought of truly epic proportions,
延續了好幾十年
lasting for many decades.
雨停了 莊稼枯萎
rains stopped, crops withered,
遍地是饑荒與混亂
and there was famine and anarchy.
蠻族入侵
Barbarians invaded.
許多城市的街道上都是死屍
The streets of many cities were littered with dead.
只有一種解釋
There could be only one explanation.
恩利爾 至高無上的神
Enlil, the supreme god,
他發怒了 因為
was angry because one of his temples
他的一座寺廟被摧毀
had been destroyed.
美索不達米亞人不知道
The people of Mesopotamia could not know
同樣的乾旱摧毀了
that the same drought was crushing
埃及文明的曙光
the dawning civilizations of Egypt,
還有希臘、印度
Greece, India,
巴基斯坦、中國
Pakistan and China.
地球上所有的神靈
All the gods of the Earth
一定是為什麼事情而發怒了
must have been really angry about something.
儘管有非凡的才華
For all their brilliance,
這些文明中的人
the people of those civilizations
沒想過把他們的經歷與
had no inkling they were experiencing
氣候突變聯繫起來
abrupt climate change.
3000年後 氣候突變
3,000 years later, the climate
同樣降臨另一個輝煌的文明
would change abruptly for another glorious civilization,
這一次是在中美洲
this one in Central America.
在文明的頂峰時刻
At its peak,
瑪雅文明消失了
the Mayan civilization perished,
被一系列的乾旱所毀滅
wiped out by a series of severe droughts
乾旱延續了一個世紀
over the course of a century.
我們依然記得
We still carry within us
這些已經滅絕文明的故事
the echoes of these extinct civilizations
留在了我們的語言與神話裏
in our languages and our myths.
今天 人類迎來了全球文明的時代
Today, we have a single global civilization.
這一次能延續多久？
How long will it live?
文明的滅絕有很多種方式
There are so many ways for a civilization to die.
讓我們從這一個
Let's start with the ones
人類對此無能為力的開始
that we probably wouldn't be able to do much about.
1000光年外的超新星爆發
That supernova is 1,000 light-years away.
它只要再近一點 比如說
If it were much closer, say...
距離地球少於30光年
less than 30 light-years from Earth,
宇宙射線就會切碎
its cosmic radiation would shred
地球大氣的臭氧保護層
the atmosphere's protective ozone layer
摧毀我們的文明
and destroy our civilization.
幸運的是 距離我們那麼近的恆星裏
Lucky for us, none of the stars close enough to harm us
起碼在未來的幾百萬年裏
are likely to go supernova
沒有一顆會變成超新星
any time in the next few hundred million years.
每隔一百萬年左右
Every million years or so,
地球上會有一座超大型火山爆發
a supervolcano erupts somewhere on Earth.
最近的一次是七萬四千年以前
The last time it happened was 74,000 years ago,
在蘇門答臘島上
on the island of Sumatra,
也就是今天的印度尼西亞
in what is now Indonesia.
它噴出的
It spewed hundreds of times more
岩石、火山灰和有毒氣體
rock, ash and toxic gas
比有記載以來的任何一座火山都要超出百倍
than any single volcano in recorded history.
熔岩從地殼中爆發出來
The molten rock that erupted from Earth's crust
離開這個火山口
left this caldera,
綿延100公里
100 kilometers long,
這裏現在形成了一個湖
now filled with a lake.
多巴火山把超過600立方英里的碎石拋向天空
The Toba volcano sent more than 600 cubic miles of pulverized rock soaring skyward.
西風把火山灰帶到了印度
The westward wind carried the volcanic ash over India,
就像一塊厚厚的毛毯那樣
where it fell out in a smothering blanket
覆蓋了整個印度次大陸
over the subcontinent.
這次爆發讓地球的上層大氣充滿了硫
The eruption loaded the upper atmosphere with sulfur gases.
形成了全球性的霧霾天氣
The result was a global haze
阻擋了大部分的陽光
that blocked most of the sunlight
照射到地面 並持續了至少5年
from reaching the surface for at least five years.
就好像是一個延續了5年的陰天
It was like one five-year-long cloudy day.
這就是所謂的"火山冬天"
This so-called "volcanic winter"
它類似於"核冬天"  但是沒有輻射
resembled a "nuclear winter," but without the radiation.
全球氣溫下降
Temperatures fell everywhere.
即使是在熱帶地區 動植物都會被凍住
Plants and animals froze even in the tropics,
死亡的更是不計其數
dying in enormous numbers.
但生命是頑強的
But life is hardy.
只有很少一部分物種遭到滅絕
Only a few species were driven to extinction.
在印度中部生活的一位古人
One of our ancestors in central India
就在多巴火山爆發的前1年
sharpened this stone blade
把這塊石頭磨成了石刀
in the years before the Toba eruption.
而這一塊石刀
And this blade
是人們發現的十幾把石刀中的一把
was one of dozens that were found
它就在火山灰上的那一層土裏
in the soil layer above the volcanic fallout.
這說明做這些工具的人
This tells us that some toolmakers,
雖然他們就生活在直接受火山影響的地區
even in the area directly affected by the volcano,
依然設法在這場大災變中生存下來
managed to survive the cataclysm.
但當時的全球人口
But the global human population
必定暴跌 然後又出現了回升
must have plummeted before rebounding.
如果明天就有這樣一場火山爆發
If an eruption like this were to happen tomorrow,
即使人類能倖存下來
our civilization would be brought to its knees,
我們的文明也會一蹶不振
although the human species would survive.
可以設想 我們的科技在幾百年後
I can imagine that our technology of a few hundred years from now
可以讓我們吸取
would allow us to siphon off
在火山即將爆發的時刻
the energy of a threatening supervolcano
具有威脅性的那些能量
before it explodes.
我們還能把這些能量化為己用
We could then use that energy for our own purposes.
每隔那麼幾百萬年
About once every million years, a small asteroid
就會有一顆小行星碰撞地球
collides with the Earth,
造成類似的破壞
causing a similar amount of devastation.
根據我們現有的科技
With our current science and technology,
人類已經知道如何避免小行星衝撞
we already know how to prevent an asteroid impact.
我們能提早數年發現它的到來
We would see it coming years in advance
並把航天飛行器送到那裏
and could send a spacecraft there
將它轉移到一個不會造成傷害的軌道
to deflect it into a harmless orbit.
幾千年後 也許我們的科技
With the technology of a thousand years from now,
已經發展到能讓我們減輕
we might even be able to mitigate the deadly effects
在地球附近爆發的超新星的影響
of a nearby supernova on Earth's atmosphere.
但如果降臨人類的危險是悄無聲息的
But what happens when the danger to a civilization is invisible?
沒人可以預見 那又該如何是好
When no one can see it coming?
繼哥倫布之後
Beginning with Columbus,
歐洲人不斷侵略美洲
the European invaders of the Americas
他們攜帶著自己也不知道的秘密武器
had a secret weapon that even they knew nothing about.
就是他們攜帶的細菌與病毒
They were carrying bacteria and viruses
那是致命的疾病 比如天花
for deadly diseases, such as smallpox,
美洲的原住民從未接觸過
that the original Americans had never been exposed to.
歐洲人總以為
The Europeans like to believe
是他們的勇氣和長槍利炮
that it was their valor and superior weapons
還有優越的文化讓他們征服了新大陸
and culture that won them the New World.
但真正的征服者
The real conquistadors were
是比人跑得更快的病原體軍隊
the armies of the pathogens that raced on ahead
它們感染並殺死了在北美洲、中美洲、南美洲
to infect and kill nine out of ten of all the Indians
近九成的印第安人
of North, Central and South America.
新大陸的偉大文明
The great civilizations of the New World
在入侵微生物的攻擊下崩潰了
crumbled under the onslaught of invading microbes.
沒有這支看不見的軍隊
Without his invisible army,
科爾特斯和他的小夥伴們根本沒機會征服新大陸
Cortez and those who followed might never have stood a chance.
如果文明走向自我毀滅 又會怎樣？
But what about civilizations that self-destruct?
我們的經濟體系是建立在
Our economic systems were formed when the planet
這個星球的空氣 河流 海洋 陸地
and its air, rivers, oceans, lands,
似乎都用之不竭的假像之上
all seemed infinite.
他們在人類誕生之前
They evolved long before we first saw the Earth
早已走在進化的道路之上
as the tiny organism that it actually is.
全球經濟體系都有一個共同點
They're all alike in one respect...
那就是逐利而行
they're profit-driven,
因此 只關注眼前利益
and therefore, focused on short-term gain.
當代主要的經濟體系
The prevailing economic systems,
不管它們是姓"社"還是姓"資」"
no matter what their ideologies,
一律缺乏內在的機制來保護我們的子孫後代
have no built-in mechanisms for protecting our descendants
哪怕是100年都沒有
of even 100 years from now,
更不要說一萬年了
let alone, 100,000.
從某個方面來說 我們做得比
In one respect, we're ahead
古代的美索不達米亞人更偏激
of the people of Ancient Mesopotamia.
和他們不同的是 我們知道自己在做什麼
Unlike them, we understand what's happening to our world.
例如 人類以地球在過去100萬年裏未有的速度
For example, we're pumping greenhouse gases into our atmosphere at a rate not seen on Earth
向地球排放溫室氣體
for a million years.
科學界的共識是
And the scientific consensus
人類在讓氣候變得不穩定
that we're destabilizing our climate.
然而 我們的文明似乎對此又不已為然
Yet our civilization seems to be in the grip of denial;
陷入了麻木不仁的境地
a kind of paralysis.
人們知道的是一回事
There's a disconnect between what we know
做的又是另外一回事
and what we do.
能讓自已的行為適應環境的變化
Being able to adapt our behavior to challenges
是人類智慧的體現
is as good a definition of intelligence as any I know.
如果說高級的智慧是我們物種的標誌
If our greater intelligence is the hallmark of our species,
那我們就應該好好利用它
then we should use it,
其它的物種都在利用它們的獨特優勢
as all other beings use their distinctive advantages--
來讓自己的後代繁榮昌盛
to help ensure that their offspring prosper,
讓它們的遺傳得以流傳
and their heredity is passed on,
這是自然界的基本體系 維繫著人類的生存
and that the fabric of nature that sustains us is protected.
當然 人的智慧是不完美的
Human intelligence is imperfect, surely,
這就產生了很多新問題
and newly arisen.
人很容易被甜言所惑 不知所措
The ease with which it can be sweet-talked, overwhelmed,
或是曲從於強權
or subverted by other hard-wired tendencies,
有時候還會假借理性來掩蓋內心的擔憂
sometimes themselves disguised as the light of reason, is worrisome.
可如果智慧是我們最大的優勢
But if our intelligence is the only edge,
我們就該善用它
we must learn to use it better.
改進它
To sharpen it.
瞭解它的局限與不足
To understand its limitations and deficiencies.
像自然界的動物一樣
To use it as cats use stealth before pouncing.
不濫用它的力量
As walking sticks use camouflage.
讓它成為人類生存的工具
To make it the tool of our survival.
如果人類能做到這一點
If we do this, we can solve
那麼在未來的10萬年裏
almost any problem we are likely to confront
一切困難都能迎刃而解
in the next 100,000 years.
現在 我們來到了
And now we've arrived at the place
古人夢想中的不朽之地
where our ancient dreams of immortality
也是現代天文學關注的焦點
and modern astrophysics converge.
巨橢圓星系
Giant elliptical galaxies
它看上去有點像佛羅里達州
are something like... Florida,
在那裏可能有著宇宙最古老的恆星
where the oldest stars in the universe may be found.
這是一顆紅矮星
This is a red dwarf star,
比太陽更小更暗
smaller and fainter than our Sun.
紅矮星是宇宙中數量最多的恆星
Red dwarfs are by far the most plentiful stars in the cosmos.
它與太陽不一樣
Unlike the Sun, which is halfway through
太陽正處於近100億年壽命的中途
its 10-billion-year lifetime,
紅矮星則可以為它們的行星
red dwarfs will continue to provide light and warmth
提供光和熱超過上萬億年
to their planets for trillions of years.
這要比現在宇宙的年齡
That's hundreds of times longer
還要多出數百倍
than the present age of the universe.
如果智能生命可以永恆存在
What would intelligent beings do
他們會做些什麼
if they had an eternity
來拓展他們對於宇宙的瞭解？
to develop their understanding of the universe?
也許他們能找到在宇宙開啟
Perhaps they would learn how to open shortcuts
時空隧道的方法
in the fabric of spacetime,
從而在不同的星系之間
to travel between galaxies
以比光速更快的速度旅行
faster than the speed of light.
也許他們能創造出全新的宇宙
Maybe they would create whole new universes
就像是藝術或科學的實驗
as artistic or scientific experiments.
可現在 至少是在地球上
Of course no one, or at least nobody on Earth,
沒人知道永生的人會做什麼
knows what the immortals might do.
只要發揮一下無限的想像力
If one allows the imagination free reign.
可我們呢？
But what about us?
我們的未來會是怎樣？
What is our own future?
宇宙的年歷
What would the Cosmic Calendar
在下一個140億年裏會是什麼樣子？
of the next 14 billion years look like?
如果最初的宇宙年歷
If the original Cosmic Calendar
包含了宇宙誕生至今的所有時間
includes all of time from the birth of the universe
直到現在這一刻
until this very moment...
那麼宇宙的年歷
what would the Cosmic Calendar look like
在下一個140億年裏會是什麼樣子？
for the next 14 billion years?
和過去的宇宙年歷一致
Just as with the Cosmic Calendar of the past,
未來年歷上的每個月
every month the future calendar
都相當於10億年
equals about a billion years;
每一天相當於4千萬年
every day, some 40 million.
科學使我們可以預測
Science makes it possible for us to foretell
未來的某些天文事件
certain astronomical events
即使它發生在想像不到的遙遠未來
in the unimaginably distant future--
例如 太陽的死亡
the death of the Sun, for example.
在大約50億年後
In some five billion years,
這顆恆星會耗盡它的氫
our star will have exhausted its hydrogen--
那是它的核能來源
the nuclear fuel that powers it--
成為一顆紅巨星
becoming a red giant.
這聽起來很讓人絕望
I know that sounds depressing,
但如果人類能發揮出智慧
but if we apply our intelligence, our descendants
我們在那遙遠未來的後代
of that distant future will have long departed
也許早已遠離了太陽系這個失落的世界
from the lost worlds of the Sun.
天曉得
Who knows?
人類的活動帶來了太多的變數
Human events entail too many variables,
有太多的不確定性
too many uncertainties,
很難做出對人類未來的科學預測
to make scientific statements about our future.
但我們依然夢想
But we can still dream.
人類的下一個黃金年代
The next golden age of human achievement
就開啟於眼前此刻
begins here and now--
第二個宇宙年的元旦
New Year's Day of the next cosmic year.
在最初的十分之一秒內
In the first tenth of a second,
人人都關愛藍色的地球
we take the vision of the pale blue dot to heart,
學習與他人一同共享這個世界
and learn how to share this tiny world with each other.
最後一台內燃機
The last internal combustion engine
被放進了博物館
is placed in a museum,
人對於氣候的影響變小以至於消失
as the effects of climate change reverse and diminish.
在未來的五分之一秒內
A fifth of a second into this future
人類不再因貧窮而死去
people will stop dying from the effects of poverty.
地球實現了完全的自給自足
The planet is now a completely self-sustaining,
成為一個互通有無的大組織
intercommunicating organism.
半秒過後
A half-second from now,
極地的冰帽開始
the polar ice caps are restored
恢復到19世紀的水平
to the way they were in the 19th century,
氣候將會更加溫和宜人
and the forecast is mild and pleasant
在下一個1分半鍾裏
for the next cosmic minute and a half--
也就是4萬年
40,000 years.
到了人類已經開始
By the time we are ready to settle
向最近的宜居星球殖民的時候
even the nearest other planetary systems,
世界已然大不同了
we will have changed.
這簡短的一段已然經過了許多代人
The simple passage of so many generations
人類將會改變
will have changed us.
自然規律會改變我們
Necessity will have changed us.
我們是善於適應環境的種族
We are an adaptable species.
不會是像我們這樣的人抵達
It will not be we who reach Alpha Centauri
半人馬星座或者其它的恆星星系
and the other nearby star systems
乘坐著星際方舟
on our interstellar arks.
那應該是一個很像我們的物種
It will be a species very like us,
比我們更強又沒有我們的缺點
but with more of our strengths and fewer of our weaknesses;
更有自信 目光遠大
more confident, far-seeing,
更有能力和智慧
capable and wise.
雖然我們有種種弱點
For all our failings,
缺陷和局限性
despite our flaws and limitations,
但我們人類仍可稱得上偉大
we humans are capable of greatness.
有什麼夢想在我們這個時代無法實現的話
What new wonders, undreamt of in our time,
也會在下一代得以成真
will we have accomplished in another generation...
或是再下下一代
and another?
我們這飄泊的種族
How far will our nomadic species
是否還要在下個世紀末
have wandered by the end of the next century,
或下一個千禧年時繼續漫遊？
and the next millennium?
我們遙遠的後代們
Our remote descendants,
也許能安逸地活在其它的星球上
safely arrayed on many worlds
遍佈整個太陽系甚至更遙遠的地方
throughout the solar system and beyond,
他們將會團結在共同的傳統之下
will be unified by their common heritage,
共同關注著他們的家園
by their regard for their home planet,
共同分享著知識
and by their knowledge that, whatever other life may be,
不管其它的生命是何種形式
the only humans in all the universe
宇宙中只有人類是來自地球
came from Earth.
他們將會把目光集聚在
They will gaze up and strain to find
天空中那藍色的小點上
the blue dot in their skies.
他們會驚嘆
They will marvel at how vulnerable
我們擁有的潛力曾經是何等的脆弱
the repository of all our potential once was,
我們的早期是何等的險惡
how perilous our infancy,
我們的起源是何等的卑微
how humble our beginnings,
我們又跨越了多少的險阻
how many rivers we had to cross...
才找到了這條大道
before we found our way.
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息